Hi and welcome back. This is Dr. Dan
here and what we're going to be looking
at is stokometry.
So stochometry is one of those really
big concepts that we go over in general
chemistry and this can be one of the
scarier concepts that you can go across.
So we're going to go over exactly what
this is about and what you need to know.
So when it comes to stochometry, the
whole idea is that these are chemical
calculations to measure the amount of
reactants and products in a chemical
reaction. So what we're going to be
trying to do is putting chemical
reactions to work, which is all going to
answer a bunch of different questions.
So when we're looking at those
questions, we want to know how do how
much are we going to make of a different
product when we are mixing these
different vessels together? how much
reactant will I need to make this
reaction happen. It helps save a lot of
time for a chemist. It gives you that
ability to be able to predict things
which is crucial when we are looking at
individual chemical reactions. We want
to be able to predict. So that's one of
the things we're going to be looking
into in this video as we start to move
forward. And I'm going to go through a
bunch of easy tips to be able to see
exactly how we can go through
stochometric equations.
So as we go through these these
different videos, what exactly is our
goal? Well, and the goal is always the
mole. What we are always trying to do is
convert from one unit to another. So
when we go through these, we're always
trying to convert from let's say from
moles to moles or from g to g. We're
trying to do simple ratios. So like we
said, we're putting chemical reactions
to work. So stochometry it starts at the
balanced chemical reaction. Meaning that
if I take a simple reaction, let's say
if we have zinc in HCl, when these
reactants are coming together, if I put
zinc in hydrochloric acid, well, what is
going to happen? Well, we're going to
see a single replacement reaction,
meaning that we're going to be taking
that zinc atom and it's going to be
replacing
the the hydrogen and the HCl. So when
that occurs, we're going to be creating
zinc chloride and H2 gas, which if you
remember YH2, this is one of our
datomics. So it's one of those seven
diatomics that we always see all the
time. So single replacement, they follow
that A + B C A plus B formula. So that's
our little recipe we are going to follow
to help predict this reaction. And then
what we're going to do is make sure we
swap, drop it, and then balance it.
Which if you need help with trying to
balance chemical reactions, look at my
previous video on types of chemical
reactions and how to balance chemical
reactions. So the big thing is here.
What does this formula tell us? There is
a story that is hidden inside of the
coefficients. The coefficients reveal
exactly what it is that is inside of
this particular formula. It gives us an
a preview of really what to expect here
which is always very very powerful for
us. So let's take a look at it. What
exactly is it that we are seeing? Well,
if we look directly at these
coefficients, we can see that one mole
of zinc when it's put in this reaction,
it needs to react with two moles of HCl
for a complete reaction. We can also see
that one mole of zinc will create one
mole of zinc chloride or that one mole
of zinc will create one mole of hydrogen
gas. It tells a story of how much is
needed and how much you are going to
create. So how many atoms or how much
mass goes in and how much mass comes
out. Now that's not the only thing. You
can tell this also from HCl as well or
any of the species. You can say 2 moles
of HCl is equivalent to one mole of zinc
chloride made or that two moles of HCl
is equivalent to one mole of hydrogen
gas uh actually shown. So these
coefficients they represent moleto mole
conversions which is one of the most
important things that you need to know
for stoeometry.
So with that being said how can we do
these? So this is a how-to guide. So the
first thing that you need to do is
balance that chemical equation. Next
what you're going to have to do the
second step is use that mole to mole
ratio to represent the species that are
in it. But you need to have a balance in
order to do that. So make sure you're
practicing how to balance. So but the
thing is like do you measure moles in
lab? And the quick answer is no. We
don't have the a mometer to be able to
measure that. That's not something we do
measure. But we do measure mass. We can
go from mass of we can start off our
experiment. We can go to our little
balance, measure the mass of one thing.
We can use molar mass to convert that to
moles which we can then do our mole to
mole ratio to then get to the a new
product and then convert it to mass
again. So with all this being said we
have a bridge between all these
different species. We can go from mass
of a or our reactants in this case to
moles of our reactants a that I have
labeled here. Or when we go through
this, we can also then we can convert
that to our multim mole conversion
whether it be reactants or products like
how we just looked at with our zinc uh
zinc uh reaction and that can be
converted then to mass. It is a bridge.
Stoometry puts our equation to work to
help us be able to balance things. Now
so our previous equation we have to add
a step here. So being that we start with
mass versus moles, we have to add that
in as number two here and move our mole
to mole ratio down. So our step-to-step
guide is we need to balance the chemical
equation. Start with mass of A, convert
it using molar mass and then we are
going to use the mole to mole ratio to
convert to other species that we are
interested in trying to represent. Are
we trying to figure out how much product
are we making? how much of whatever this
individual reactant is. It's all about
putting the pieces together. Then our
last and fourth step is converting moles
of our product to g or the mass of to
using molar mass again. So it's four
steps to do all these stochometric
problems. So I would recommend writing
this down. You will need this for
chemistry to help pass help pass
chemistry. So let's take a look at this.
Let's do an example. So if I have the
following problem where I have butane
gas, it's a hydrocarbon and it's
undergoing combustion to produce carbon
dioxide and water. So let's go through
our steps. The first step is that we
have to balance the chemical equation.
So if you remember from types of
chemical equations, there are five major
general chemistry reactions. One of them
was combustion, meaning that a
hydrocarbon is always reacting with
oxygen to create water and CO2. So let's
do it. So we'll write out first all the
individual elements for each species. We
will count everything on all sides. And
one of the little things is when it
comes to trying to balance these
equations, when we see that we have
multiple oxygen sources on the right
hand side of the equation, right? We
have oxygen coming from water and from
CO2. This can be a little tricky in
order to balance right as a total it has
three total moles of oxygen on the right
hand side of the products is we have to
first try to even out the oxygens. So if
we do that one of the things that we are
looking at here is can we easily do
that. So if I start with trying to put a
let's say a five in front of the
hydrogens's meaning I have I'm right now
I'm looking at the hydrogen's on both
sides of the equation. We have 10 on the
left and right now we have 10 on the
right. If I do that though one thing you
will see is that the oxygens will still
remain odd overall. we'll have five
oxygen from water, two from CO2, which
is not going to ever even out,
especially when we have four carbons on
the left. So, it's one of those tricks
that if you see that this is odd, try to
first
double the amount of butane that we have
or whatever your hydrocarbon is in the
reaction. So, if we double the amount of
butane, one thing it's going to do is
help us even out all of our individual
coefficients that we have here. So, when
we balance out our hydrogens, we then
have an even number of oxygens, which
then allows us to quickly
balance the entire equation, right? And
if worst comes to worse, if you have too
many of something, uh let's say if you
can divide everything by two or by
three, you can always simplify the
equation in the end by doing that little
multiply by two trick. And then the last
thing we always do is we save oxygen for
last. So going through this, what we're
our next step was is now that we have a
balanced equation, we need to convert
mass of our reactants to moles. Now in
the original equation, I forgot to write
down how much mass there was. But one
thing that we are given in this problem
is that we have 236.5
g of butane that is being used. And we
want to know is how much CO2 will be
generated. So if I'm going to be burning
a flame, I want to know how much gas am
I going to be creating that it could be
potentially breathing in or creating
within this reaction. So when it comes
to industry or pharmaceutical industry,
we want to try to figure out how much
are we going to be creating. We want to
know we want to maximize our our our
profits or reduce our danger risks that
are in a equation. So when we do this,
we are going to be setting up our TA
table to try to show this conversion. So
if you remember, first we go from mass,
then we do molar mass of butane. So, we
add up all four carbons, the 10
hydrogens in this, and then as we go
through it, we'll see that the molar
mass is 58.12 g of butane, and that's
equivalent to 1 mole of butane. So, when
we set this up, we can cancel out our g,
which will then allow us to acquire
moles. Now, is this the final
expression? Well, we want to get to g.
So step three is the mole to mole
expression. So the beauty of stochometry
is you can set this up to be one big
calculation just like dimensional
analysis from when you first started
general chemistry. So if you take those
moles, you're going to then look at your
chemical equation, which tells that
coefficient story of if I have 2 moles
of butane that's going to be used, it's
going to create 8 moles of CO2 as a
result. So, and that's the wonder about
it. So, this allows you to be like an
alchemist showing I'm going to be
converting this to another ingredient.
So now step four is taking those moles,
converting it to grams. So we'll set up
our last step using molar mass again to
help show that all right, we're going to
follow this step by step. Mass to moles
to moles. Molar mass is going to be used
to get to our final mass. So we'll take
one mole of CO2 is equivalent to 44.01 g
of CO2, which we once again get from our
periodic table. And then we can show
units are cancelling, right? So the same
color cancels same color. And that gives
us our final thing, which is that we're
going to make 716 g of CO2 from this
reaction.
Now, when you're going through these,
are you how do you figure out how many
sigfigs? Depending on your professor or
your teacher, sigfigs may be very
crucial, and it's always important when
it comes to the lab. So when it comes to
lab generally it's whatever your
measured number is that you started from
the beginning. So if you are working
with a balance measuring out how much
let's say how much butane you had or how
much of an ingredient you had you're
going to go off your chemical balance
from the start or whatever your glassear
was that's in the lab. So on a
stoeometry problem it's always generally
whatever the number is that you started
with. It's not molar mass that limits
you. Now looking at it all, putting it
all together. So the big thing here is
how to solve it, what the final
conclusions are. The beauty of
stochometry is that it follows a very
set equation every time.
Meaning that in order to solve a massto
mass stochometry equation, you're always
doing the same steps. You balance the
chemical equation. You start with your
mass, convert it to moles using molar
mass. You'll then have that reactant
which you'll then go convert it to
either another reactant or another
product using the mole to mole ratio.
From there, you can then convert it to
grams using molar mass. And that's how
you solve stochometry problems. And this
is just the beginning. There's more to
this. Remember, the goal is always the
mole. If you can get to moles, you can
convert it to mass, to volume, to gases,
liquids, you name it. And we're going to
look at future videos to help show that.
If you like this video, please consider
liking and subscribing. And I hope to
see you in the future. This has been Dr.
Dan, and I hope this video helped you,
and hope you all have a wonderful day.
Bye now.
[Music]